Guide to the Dr. William Griffith papers, 1960-2014 MS1006.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Dr. William Griffith papers
1960-2014
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Griffith, Patricia Browning
MS1006.UA
22.5 Linear Feet 18 record center cartons
William B. Griffith joined the George Washington University faculty in July 1964 and was Elton Professor of Philosophy and Public Policy. The collection contains his work in the department, as well as other professional activities such as the faculty senate and papers given at conferences.
Scope and Contents
William B. Griffith was Elton Professor of Philosophy and Public Policy at George Washington University. He joined the GW faculty in July 1964. He devised and taught more than 30 courses during his tenure, with a special emphasis on ethical theory, philosophical aspects of public policy issues, economic justice and logic. Dr. Griffith served several terms as chair of the Department of Philosophy and was one of the longest-serving members of the Faculty Senate, where he occupied several different leadership positions.
Biographical / Historical
William B. Griffith was Elton Professor of Philosophy and Public Policy at George Washington University. William Byron Griffith was born in Fort Worth and was a 1958 graduate of the University of Notre Dame in South Bend, Ind. After studying at the University of Louvain in Belgium on a Fulbright scholarship, he received master's (1962) and doctoral degrees (1963) in philosophy from Yale University. He served in the Army before joining GWU in July 1964.
His research interests and publications focused on the application of theories of distributive justice to environmental policy, welfare policy, tax policy, and the regulation of business. He devised and taught more than 30 courses during his tenure, with a special emphasis on ethical theory, philosophical aspects of public policy issues, economic justice and logic. He was the principal architect and long-serving director of the MA Program in Philosophy and Public Policy, the first of its kind in the United States.
Dr. Griffith served several terms as chair of the Department of Philosophy and was one of the longest-serving members of the Faculty Senate, where he occupied several different leadership positions, including chair of the Executive Committee, and chair of the Committee on Fiscal Planning and Budgeting. He also served as the redoubtable parliamentarian for Columbian College faculty meetings through the fall of 2013.
He died at midnight on February 10, 2014.
Conditions Governing Access
Some materials are restricted, such as student information and salary information. Please check with the University Archivist.
Faculty; Public policy; Griffith, Patricia Browning
- Philosophy Department, 1964-2014; MS1006 Series 1
  Scope and content notes
  Records relating to the classes that Dr. Griffith was involved with during his tenure at GWU. He devised and taught more than 30 courses during his tenure, with a special emphasis on ethical theory, philosophical aspects of public policy issues, economic justice and logic
  Conditions Governing Access
  The letters of recommendations are restricted for 25 years from the date written.
  - Clippings about Philosophy Department, 1992-2014 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Philosophy - Feminist Perspective, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Education - MBA and Ethics, 1988-1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Education - Humor, 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Philosophy - General Views of, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Philosophy - Gourmet, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - American Philosophical Association - Current File, 1998-2005 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Philosophy - Outline, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Philosophy at the New Millennium, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Philosophy Department Photograph, Fall 1978 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Proposed Institute of Corporate Responsibility, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Business Ethics Chair - Search Committee, 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Ethics and Policy - Campaign Finance Clippings, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Criminal Justice, 1979-2001 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Ethics and Policy - Sentencing Papers, 1977-2004 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Ethics and Justice - Death Penalty, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Ethics and Policy - Enterprise Liability, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Ethics and Policy - Liability Reform, 1994-1999 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Ethics and Policy - Privacy Clippings, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Ethics and Policy - Pharmaceutical Policies, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Ethics and Policy - Workers' Compensation, 1985-1995 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Economic Justice, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Ethics and Policy - State Gambling, 1995-2005 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Ethics and Educational Policy, 1996-2005 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Provost Office Semester Welcome Letter, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Graduate Studies Budget, 2007-2008 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Ethics and Policy - Patriot Act, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Ethics and Policy - Anti-Immigration Statistics, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Ethics and Policy - Social Isolation, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Socioeconomics, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 35-36)
  - GW Seminars - Socio-Economics, 1985-1995 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Philosophy and Ethics topics and courses, 1992-2008; 1.25 Cubic Feet One box (Box 3)
    Scope and contents note
    Program description, specific classes in Philosophy and ethics such as 51, 131, 132, 801, 230, rights theory, feminist, more development, welfare and food stamps. Documents within the folder include handouts, syllabi, bibliographies
  - Philosophy Department Files, 2006-2012; 1.25 Cubic Feet 1 Box (Box 4)
    Box contains folders pertaining to prospective students, search committees for the department, general philosophy department records, specific classes such as 6230, and policy guides for students, admininstration, applications, inquiries, course description and jobs.
  - Office Files, 1974-2007 (Box 5, Folder 24-65)
    Philosophy classes - 230 (2004-2007) with student evaluationss; criminal justice and discrimination; family support act of 1988; lawsuits that had to do with philosophical ideas; justice and equality from 1974, conference on social security from 1986. Ethics and sociology issues such as regulation, academic, and professionalism.
  - Philosophy Department Files, 1987-2009; 1.25 Cubic Feet 1 Box (Box 6)
    Ethics and policy - discrimination, affirmative action, general data, views and economic theories, justice, equality and gender, and different legal cases. Specific classes such as 131, 132, 801, 198 and 235.
  - Philosophy Department Records, 1979-1998; 1.25 Linear Feet 1 box (Box 7)
    Scope and Contents
    Philosophy courses such as 235, philosophy and business, philosophy and public interest, and other related topics to these classes.
  - Lecture Material for Ethics and Philosophy Courses, 1979-2003; 1.25 Linear Feet (Box 9, Folder 1-37)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1995 (Box 9, Folder 38-40)
  - Letters of Recommendation, 1993-2004 (Box 9, Folder 41-45)
    Restricted for 25 years from date of creation.
  - Philosophy 201 readings and research (Box 10, Folder 51)
  - Dissertation and paper proposals (Box 10, Folder 52-59)
  - Academic calendars and plans (Box 10, Folder 60-62)
  - Fellowship mentor program, 1997-2006 (Box 10, Folder 63-64)
  - University Facilitating Fund Request for Proposals (Box 10, Folder 65)
  - GWU strategic plan, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 66)
  - GWU Unionization, 2004-2005 (Box 10, Folder 67)
  - Background information for classes, 1994-1999 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Economics and Philosophy, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Economics and Philosophy 241-242, Labor Economics, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - History of Economic Thought, Economy 202, 1996-1997 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Economy as Discipline, 2003 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Ethics and Economics, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 6-7)
  - Policy Science Research, 1972-1992 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Ethics and Policy Field Issues, 1989-1994 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Policy Analysis, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Ethics and Policy: Rational Choice Models and Risk Assessment, 1983-1988 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Ethics and Policy, 1978-1993 (Box 11, Folder 12-14)
  - Policy Courses, 1986-1991 (Box 11, Folder 15-16)
  - Department Faculty Publications, 1993-1994 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Expressive Meaning, Race and the Law, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Department Faculty Papers, 1994-1997 (Box 11, Folder 19-26)
  - Ethics Academic Papers, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 27-31)
  - Philosophy of the Mind, 2001-2005 (Box 11, Folder 32)
  - Philosophy 231 Economic Justice, 1989-2007 (Box 12, Folder 1-5)
  - Philosophy 235 Ethics and Business, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Philosophy 242, 1994-2005 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Philosophy 238 Feminist Ethics, 1997-1999 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Philosophy 281 Environmental Philosophy and Policy, 2005 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Notes on organizing a research paper, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Guidance on participation in class discussion, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Course evaluations, 1999-2010 (Box 12, Folder 12-15)
  - Philosophy Department questions (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Book adoption fees and reserve, 2011 (Box 12, Folder 17-18)
  - Records, 2007-2009 (Box 13, Folder 24-25)
  - Public Policy and Public Administration, 2003-2008 (Box 13, Folder 26-27)
  - Public Policy PhD Field Exam Questions, 2006 (Box 13, Folder 28)
    This folder is restricted.
  - Public Policy courses, 2003-2006 (Box 13, Folder 29-31)
  - Doctoral Program Reviews and Committee, 2004 (Box 13, Folder 32-33)
    This may be restricted.
  - Public Policy program materials, 2002-2003 (Box 13, Folder 34-35)
  - General Philosophy Department materials, Circa 1996-2012 (Box 14)
  - Professional Ethics and Philosophy, 1982-1998; This box contains a wide variety of topics in the realm of ethics, economy and philosophy such as professional accountability, hedge funds, taxes, government and public administration, legal ethics, medicine, and social work. The papers appear to be research that was sometimes used in Dr. Griffith's classes. (Box 16)
  - Philosophy Notes and Writings, 1960-1985; Notes and writings on philosophical topics such as logic, logicism, finitism, Godel's Theorem, the history and philosophy of math and logic, valued logic and the philosophy of language. These appear to be copies of articles or presentations that Griffith attended and made notes. Some of these may be notes that Griffith himself took while a student. (Box 17)
  - Philosophy Notes and Writings, 1967-1989; Notes and writings on philosophical topics such as symbolic logic, logical theory, advanced logic, logic and social change, logic of choice and decisions, cryptography, and axiomatics. These appear to be copies of articles or presentations that Griffith attended and made notes. Some of these may be notes that Griffith himself took while a student. (Box 18)
- Faculty Senate, 1978-2014; MS1006 Series 2
  Dr. Griffith was one of the longest-serving members of the Faculty Senate, where he occupied several different leadership positions, including chair of the Executive Committee, and chair of the Committee on Fiscal Planning and Budgeting. He also served as the redoubtable parliamentarian for Columbian College faculty meetings through the fall of 2013.
  - Budget group - faculty subgroup, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General, 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Budget working group, Spring 2006 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Fiscal Planning and Budgeting (FP&B) Committee, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General, 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General, 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General, 2007-2008 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fiscal Planning and Budgeting (FP&B) Committee, 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Fiscal Planning and Budgeting (FP&B) Committee - Documents, 2006-2007 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General, 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General, 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Fiscal Planning and Budgeting (FP&B) Committee, 2006-2007 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Fiscal Planning and Budgeting (FP&B) Committee, 2012-2013 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Fiscal Planning and Budgeting (FP&B) Committee, 2011-2012 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Fiscal Planning and Budgeting (FP&B) Committee - Documents, endowment, 2006-2007 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - CCAS By-Laws, Policies and Rules, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - CCAS By-Laws - Revision Proposal, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Trachtenberg School By-Laws, 2005-2011 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Trachtenberg School Faculty Meeting, 2011-2012 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Fiscal Planning and Budgeting (FP&B) Committee, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Fiscal Planning and Budgeting (FP&B) Committee - Enrollment and Endowment, 1999-2005 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fiscal Planning and Budgeting (FP&B) Committee - Enrollment and Faculty Needs, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Fiscal Planning and Budgeting (FP&B) Committee - Junior Subcommittee Athletics and Recreation, 2002-2004 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - School of Nursing, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Office Files, 1996-2001; 1.25 Cubic Feet One box This box shares items between both series. (Box 5, Folder 1-23)
    University policies - code of academic integrity (1996); disabilities, media relations, Gelman fines, student rights and responsibilities, requirements in syllabi, and Trachtenberg prize. Also includes the Faculty Senate trustees committee and development of alumni, 2000-2001
  - Letters of recommendation, 1983-1994; 1.25 Linear Feet 1 box (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
    General
    This file may contain sensitive information.
  - General, 1999-2002 (Box 8, Folder 4-7)
  - Fiscal Planning and Budgeting (FP&B) Committee, 1996-2012 (Box 8, Folder 8-15)
  - Faculty Senate Fiscal Planning and Budgeting Committee, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 33)
  - Salary Equity Revisions, 1998-2000 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Restrictions apply to this folder.
  - Salary Reviews, 1995-1996 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee, Non-Tenure Data, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    This folder may have restrictions.
  - Special Committee on Non-Tenure Accruing Appointments, 1989-1990 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Academic Freedom and Tenure, 1980-1996 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Professional Ethics Committee, 1978-1989 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Professional Ethics Tenure Criteria, 1982-1983 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    This folder may be restricted.
  - Special Committee on Non-Tenure Accruing Appointments, 1982-1983 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Professional Ethics Committee, 1979-1980 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Special Committee on Non-Tenure Accruing Data, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Professional Ethics, 1981-1982 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Committee on Professional Ethics and Academic Freedom, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Professional Ethics Responses to Senators, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Professional Ethics Committee, 1979-1980 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - General Faculty Senate materials, Circa 1996-2012 (Box 14)
- Conference Papers and Presentations, 1992-2012; MS1006 Series 3
  This box contains materials related to presentations at conferences, seminars and symposia. The folders contain the presentation themselves, notes, abstracts, correspondence and other related items.
  - Human Rights Treaties and Torture, Association for the Study of Law, Culture and the Humanities (ASLCH), March 2012 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - ASLCH abstract, conference info, 2012 March (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Law, Culture and the Humanities (LCH) Abstract, presentation notes, 2011 March (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - LCH Conf Presentation, notes drafts and abstract, 2010 March (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Civility Symposium panel presentation, October 2010 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Presentation to Philosophy Department, April 2010 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Presentation to LCH Conference, March 2010 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Article Review, October 2009 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - ASLCH, March 2008 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - New Direction of Humanities symposium, 2007 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Roundtable Economic Justice, April 2006 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Communitarian Summit Panel Papers, July 2008 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - North American Society for Social Philosophy, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Conference - Law, Culture and the Humanities, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - LCH Conference, March 2005 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - APPAM Research Conference Creating and Using Evidence in Public Policy Analysis and Management, October 2004 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Association of Public Policy Analysis and Management (APPAM), 2005 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - ASLCH, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - APPAM, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Presentation to Philosophy Faculty, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Comments on Liberation, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Conference of Concerned Philosophers for Peace, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Philosophy Conference, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Communitarian Summit, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - North American Society for Social Philosophy (NASSP), 2003 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Paper for Future Generations, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Conference on Value Inquiry, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Public Policy Workshop, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Communitarian Summit Labor Paper, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - LCH, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Annual Meeting of the Society for Philosophy in the Contemporary World, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Faculty brown bag discussion, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - NASSP Conference, 2009 (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - LCH, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - LCH, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - Reason in Environmental Practice (Box 10, Folder 36)
  - Moral and Political Reasoning in Environmental Practice, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 37)
  - Human Sciences Annual Conference, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 38)
  - Conference on Value Inquiry, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 39)
  - Rights and cost benefits, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 40)
  - Economics at the Millennium - copies of publications (Box 10, Folder 41)
  - Excluding inferior workers - copies of publications (Box 10, Folder 42)
  - Welfare economics papers (Box 10, Folder 43-45)
  - Nature of economics conference, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 46)
  - Fair Trade public perceptions, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 47)
  - Copies of writings (Box 10, Folder 48)
- Personal Papers, 1964-2011; MS1006 Series 4
  This series contains a small number of personal papers such as biographical information and annual reports.
  - Annual Reports, 1985-2007 (Box 12, Folder 19-20)
  - Biographical information, 1964-2011 (Box 12, Folder 21-22)
  - Promotion Papers, 1981-1983 (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Application for Fellowships, 2001-2002 (Box 12, Folder 24-25)
  - Library Study, 2001 (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Columbian College of Arts and Sciences, 2011-2012 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1986-2007 (Box 13, Folder 16-23)
  - Personal writings and reviews, 1979-1997; This box contains a variety of personal writings on philosophy and ethics topics. It includes reprints, drafts, copies, and other parts of the writing process. (Box 15)